Okay, so now we need to change the direction of our car so it doesn't just look like it's gliding across
the screen but actually turning.
And to achieve this, like with our other project we can use this point direction block.
But you might have noticed something strange if you try to use it.
And that is if you point in a straight direction and click it, you'll see our car point to the side,
which seems rather weird.
But there is some sense to this.
Scratch assumes that your sprites default direction is facing to the right.
Let's take the default cat sprite as an example.
When you bring it into your project, you'll see that it really looks like it's facing right.
So when you use a block to make it face up or zero degrees, it's actually looks like it's facing up
because it was initially facing the right.
Now, I know it's still a bit confusing, but the key here is to understand that scratch assumes all
your sprites are facing this way.
So when you create your own sprite or use a different one, just make sure to adjust its initial direction
in the costume editor so it faces the right way when you start working with it.
So moving back to our car, we can go into the editor and using this arrow, we can rotate our car to
have it face right.
And here you have it.
Now you can see that it points in the exact direction that we set it.
Great.
Now let's implement this into our code.
So quite simply what we want is to look like it's turning right when we click the right arrow and left
when we click the left arrow.
So we can just drag our point direction and put one in each of these if statements.
So for the first we can have it at about 15 degrees.
And for the second, we can set it to -50.
Now, if we hit play again and then turn, you can see it works.
Now, although there are clearly a few bugs here, the first is quite easy to dress, which is when
we start the game.
Our car kind of points to the side, which doesn't quite look right.
So we can just add a point direction to the start and have it point straight on the start.
And now, as you can see, that's much better.
Although as you can also see, if we stop turning and just go straight, our car still points in whatever
direction it was last pointing.
Now this is a bit more complex, as we need a way for a car to point straight if none of the buttons
are clicked.
So once again, pause the video and try to see if you can get this to work and get the car to point
straight.
Did you figure it out?
Now looking at our code, you can see we have these two if statements that check if we are clicking
one key or the other key.
But there is another type of if statement that we haven't really used.
And it's so super important.
So if we're going down to our control, you will see we have this if else block.
And well we know what the if block does like if a condition is true it will execute some code.
Like if the right arrow is clicked, it will turn right.
And with this block it will do the same.
But if the condition is not true, it will execute any code in this else block.
So let's see this in action.
Firstly, taking all this code out we can swap it for this.
And here we can bring in if the right arrow is clicked and then point the direction and change x.
In for the elves.
Let's just bring in this other code.
Now, if you hit play, you will see that if you click the right arrow, the car does what is expected.
But if the right arrow is not clicked, the car glides to the left.
So now we understand how all that works.
Let's bring it back to how it was and a useful tip.
Just click command Z or control Z.
If you're on windows and you'll see your code revert to how it was.
So let's do this.
Let's swap out this left arrow for this if else.
And then move the code inside.
And finally in the else we can bring in a point direction and have it point straight.
Well, that makes sense.
If we click right, it points right.
If we click left, it points left.
Otherwise it points up.
So let's give that a try.
Well, that's not right, is it?
Let's try to untangle this a bit.
We have a situation where clicking right doesn't seem to work as expected, but clicking left does.
The answer lies in the order in which the code is processed.
Remember, in programming, code is run from the top to the bottom.
It checks each condition in the order they appear.
So when we click write, our sprite is indeed instructed to point right.
However, there is more code after this that the computer still has to check, which is this here.
If we click left, it will point left.
But you see here, if this condition is not true, whatever is in this block will happen.
The final block of code gives a command for the sprite to point straight.
The sprite will follow this command if this condition is not met, and because this block is last,
it's ultimately what will be executed.
Yeah, I know programming logic is quite something, but the more you really try to understand it,
the more clear it all becomes.
It's all about thinking like a computer.
So that all said, how do we fix this?
Well, in programming, you generally don't want to have a situation where there are if blocks in a
single script or loop.
Instead, what we want to use is an if else.
So instead of this code looking like this, we will grab another if else, put this code inside.
Put it in the loop.
And finally we can put this if else in this else statement.
So not if we look at the code.
If the right arrow is clicked, this will execute.
Otherwise, if the left arrow is clicked, this code will execute.
And then only if none of the above conditions are true.
No left or right is clicked.
Our car will point straight.
So playing the game again.
See now how it runs perfectly.
So adding in this if else ensures that this bottom code can only execute if we aren't clicking the right
arrow, and then only if we aren't also clicking the left arrow.
Then finally will this else execute.
Now, all this might be a little bit confusing, but this is really the essence of programming.
Just understanding the order of operations and how code is executed and organized logically.
And trust me, the more you build, the clearer it will become.
So play around with it and try to understand it because they are exciting things to come.